<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Silmaril's Blog</title><link>/</link><description>Recent content on Silmaril's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Upgrading the blog, day 360205</title><link>/blog/2022/06/18/Upgrading-the-blog-day-360205/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2022/06/18/Upgrading-the-blog-day-360205/</guid><description>So &amp;hellip;
Hi back i guess ? :)
Years have passed, the previous engine setup proved unreliable, update to jekyll, ruby, and whatever keep breaking up the thing in all ways i could not even think of.
Jekyll-assets particularly seem to have a pretty hard time keeping up with the ecosystem, so &amp;hellip; let&amp;rsquo;s try another way ?
Hugo I found this tool, Hugo ages ago, basically the same concept as jekyll but based on a go software, always wanted to do the switch hopefully it would prove more reliable ?</description></item><item><title>Setting up an HA LoadBalancer with haproxy 2.x and exabgp 4.x</title><link>/blog/2020/02/11/Setting-up-an-HA-LoadBalancer-with-haproxy-2.x-and-exabgp-4.x/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2020/02/11/Setting-up-an-HA-LoadBalancer-with-haproxy-2.x-and-exabgp-4.x/</guid><description>A few time ago i started a project of replacing our proprietary load-balancing solution. As i already previously used haproxy for the task i leaned over re-using this formidable software. However i did not wanted to use VRRP for HA-ing the lot, so there is the story of how i did this.
Schema Here is a quick schematic depicting the final configuration:
Setting up HAProxy First things first, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to add haproxy (at least 2.</description></item><item><title>Let's Encrypt Chef-Server</title><link>/blog/2019/12/06/Lets-Encrypt-Chef-Server/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2019/12/06/Lets-Encrypt-Chef-Server/</guid><description>Hi,
So today i wanted to switch our chef-server certificates from an old internal pki with issues (SHA1 &amp;hellip;) to another solution, and since we are avid users of Let&amp;rsquo;s Encrypt this was my first idea.
However i quickly stumble onto an issue, the chef-server private cookbook aren&amp;rsquo;t &amp;lsquo;compatible&amp;rsquo; with this (ie there is no way to insert some custom nginx rules on the correct location to allow serving of /.</description></item><item><title>FreeBSD DHCPv6</title><link>/blog/2018/04/22/FreeBSD-DHCPv6/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2018/04/22/FreeBSD-DHCPv6/</guid><description>In FreeBSD Setup i detailed the use of KAME&amp;rsquo;s dhcp client to authentify and request an IPv6 block to be routed onto the server.
However as it seem this client has a tendancy to misbehave and trigger the hosting provider DOS defense mechanism (mainly rebooting the serveur after disabling dhcp service autorisations, not fun).
While checking around with friend it seems i wasn&amp;rsquo;t the first one hit by this and that the solution was to switch over to ISC&amp;rsquo;s dhcp service, with a little twist (freebsd package for isc-dhcp doesn&amp;rsquo;t include an init script for dhcpv6).</description></item><item><title>Upgrading the blog, day 2</title><link>/blog/2018/04/17/Upgrading-the-blog-day-2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2018/04/17/Upgrading-the-blog-day-2/</guid><description>Last time up on setting up nginx to make PageSpeed Insight happy, we saw that tweaking the webserver wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough, so now we will have to work on the content.
Compress html output minify &amp;amp; pre-compress js/css assets optimize media assets Compress (minify) html output There are a bunch of solutions for this step, as of now i&amp;rsquo;m using the simpler approach of &amp;ldquo;jekyll-compress&amp;rdquo;, it&amp;rsquo;s an html &amp;ldquo;compressor&amp;rdquo; that work in pure &amp;ldquo;Liquid&amp;rdquo; (the templating language of jekyll), so no strange ruby installation and whatnot, you only need to fetch the compress.</description></item><item><title>Upgrading the blog, day 1</title><link>/blog/2018/04/16/Upgrading-the-blog-day-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2018/04/16/Upgrading-the-blog-day-1/</guid><description>A year has past since the beginning of this little experiment, and some results are already showing:
i&amp;rsquo;m not very prolific ^^ i&amp;rsquo;m becoming more and more grumpy i don&amp;rsquo;t like my blog&amp;rsquo;s setup (but didn&amp;rsquo;t find better for now) . So yeah, new year was 4 month ago and still nothing new here, my article on bind, dnssec and knot hasn&amp;rsquo;t moved further, but work-related issues send me back here to make some experiments, our SEO consultants where reportings issues on our client&amp;rsquo;s website and where in need of informations.</description></item><item><title>Drive Failure and reinstall</title><link>/blog/2017/10/30/Drive-Failure-and-reinstall/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2017/10/30/Drive-Failure-and-reinstall/</guid><description>Hi,
This weekend was one of thoses weekend &amp;hellip; Sunday morning while trying to destroy an unused jail i got a zfs warning: &amp;ldquo;pool is degraded&amp;rdquo;.
As it turn out i was missing a drive in my zfs mirror setup, so heck .. no fun.
After a few email with the hosting company they recommended i migrate over a new server, which is running ok if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this ;).</description></item><item><title>Poudriere</title><link>/blog/2017/05/05/Poudriere/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2017/05/05/Poudriere/</guid><description>In some cases you might need to use some customisation over the standard pre-built packages repository. Two choices there: you can either manually build them using the ports system on each of your jails/servers, or you can make a custom pkg repository with your build options.
This is what i will show here, using the poudriere build system, a creation by the same author of pkg, bapt, a good guy (yes yes ;) ) who has coped with me during many FreeBSD rants (well he wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only one, thanks Keltia , nerzhul, renchap and others for your precious help).</description></item><item><title>Setting up jails</title><link>/blog/2017/02/27/Setting-up-jails/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2017/02/27/Setting-up-jails/</guid><description>The main idea of this new setup is to try and isolate services for the main host, which should be only used for management.
So every service will be run in it&amp;rsquo;s own context, known as jails in the Free/Net/OpenBSD lingua.
However a few helping services on the host might be usefull, for DNS resolving, log collection, &amp;hellip;
Service IP Since i don&amp;rsquo;t own a lot of IPv4 public adresses, some a private IPv4 network will be used for accessing services in this network familly, and some NAT will have to be set.</description></item><item><title>Firewalling: PF</title><link>/blog/2017/02/19/Firewalling-PF/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2017/02/19/Firewalling-PF/</guid><description>So, now we have some basis of a working system.
Time to think about protecting if, while the Internet is the place to be it&amp;rsquo;s also a kind of a bad place, moreover when you&amp;rsquo;re in the middle of a known hosting company.
Firewalling So, we have to play with FreeBSD firewall solution: PF, as in Packet Filter.
Configuring So first thing is to setup a few rules in the /etc/pf.</description></item><item><title>Configuration Time</title><link>/blog/2017/02/14/Configuration-Time/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2017/02/14/Configuration-Time/</guid><description>Hi there,
Taking over where i left before, so now i do have a fresh and shiny new machine, time to set it up.
The Base System FreeBSD contrarious to linux system is separated into two main part, the main part is the &amp;ldquo;base system&amp;rdquo;, basically it&amp;rsquo;s what FreeBSD is, and is released and updated as a whole.
To keep the base system up to date we need to use the freebsd-update utility.</description></item><item><title>Installation Time</title><link>/blog/2017/02/06/Installation-Time/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 22:40:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2017/02/06/Installation-Time/</guid><description>Hi there,
Taking over where i left before, so now i do have a fresh and shiny new machine, time to set it up.
As previously stated, the intended OS for this gig is FreeBSD, so there i am, discovering the Online Administration Console, trying to figure out what to do with this stuff.
Has it happens, there are a few installation procedures availables &amp;ldquo;out-of-the-box&amp;rdquo;, letting you setup your server within the web console, for a bunch of OS, including FreeBSD, but - yeah there is always a but - the FreeBSD 11 install procedure only support the UFS filesystem.</description></item><item><title>Hello, World !</title><link>/blog/2017/02/06/Hello-World/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 22:10:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2017/02/06/Hello-World/</guid><description>Hi,
Well there is a first for everything. After fifteen year of almost pure linux/debian sysadmin, and seeing all this lunatic development under the &amp;ldquo;devops&amp;rdquo; banner, where stability is a curse, this year i wanted to try something different. So no &amp;ldquo;docker&amp;rdquo; here, well not until it&amp;rsquo;s really suitable for production use (and provided we do have a use for it), but something older and probably better (at least that&amp;rsquo;s what he said), called FreeBSD.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>/pages/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/pages/about/</guid><description>About Myself My name is Benoit Plessis and this is my blog.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been a system administrator and engineer for almost twenty years now, mostly running internet websites and this is my first real online presence :)
I am currently head of system and network infrastructure at New Oxatis a company providing SaaS solutions for retail services.
Areas of interest Books, mostly SF genre (Frank Herbert&amp;rsquo;s Dune, Dan Simmons&amp;rsquo;s Hyperion, Isaac Asimov Fondation, &amp;hellip;) but also Fantasy (Tolkien, Terry Goodkind, &amp;hellip;) Horses I&amp;rsquo;m also an amateur photograph 500px Contacts Social Medias:</description></item><item><title>CV</title><link>/draft/CV/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/draft/CV/</guid><description>Benoit Plessis 9 rue Mairan benoit@plessis.info 34500 Béziers @silmaril34 France +33 6 77 42 78 32
Experience Head of System and Network Infrastructure at DOYOUSOFT, SA:
Short text containing the type of work done, results obtained, lessons learned and other remarks. Can also include lists and links:
First item
Item with link. Links will work both in the html and pdf versions.
Network and System Administrator at the University of Le Mans:</description></item><item><title>Links</title><link>/pages/links/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/pages/links/</guid><description>Friends&amp;rsquo;s stuff:
Blue&amp;rsquo;s Blog
Keltia&amp;rsquo;s Site
Keltia&amp;rsquo;s Blog
Bapt&amp;rsquo;s Blog
Neuro&amp;rsquo;s Blog
Renchap&amp;rsquo;s Blog
Usefull stuff:
OS:
Debian FreeBSD Photo
Fred Miranda Talegraph</description></item></channel></rss>